<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.2.0">Jekyll</generator><link href="/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2021-03-23T20:44:27+00:00</updated><id>/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Other peoples’ mistakes</title><subtitle>We all make mistakes in business and I pretty much have the box set. I like to think that I've learned from those mistakes and this is where I'm going to document some of those learnings.</subtitle><entry><title type="html">An opportunity</title><link href="/time/management/task/2021/03/15/an-opportunity.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="An opportunity" /><published>2021-03-15T17:12:19+00:00</published><updated>2021-03-15T17:12:19+00:00</updated><id>/time/management/task/2021/03/15/an-opportunity</id><content type="html" xml:base="/time/management/task/2021/03/15/an-opportunity.html">&lt;p&gt;The Pandemic and lockdowns have obviously had a huge impact on how we work and have especially imposed new challenges juggling the work / life balance. In turn this has meant that some tried and tested methods for managing tasks and actually completing them are failing.&lt;br /&gt;
This is my attempt to find another way that works for me.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1&gt;The Scenario&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Recently I have been given an opportunity to try out new ways of working in a risk free environment as I have been furloughed from my role.&lt;br /&gt;
I’m lucky enough to work for one of the most exciting startups that I have been involved with for some time and it really is a great business, but the pandemic has caused chaos with cashflow at a critical juncture in its funding cycle. We’d already furloughed down to the bare bones and stepping away from the business until circumstances change was absolutely the right move. So, in the spirit of sharpening my axe whilst I’m taking a break from chopping down trees; I thought that I would reflect on my working habits and try some experiments with new ways of working.&lt;br /&gt;
I like to keep dabbling away on side projects as and when I can (see more about side projects) and while I’ve been working hard in startup land a whole load of household tasks and DIY projects have fallen by the wayside. I’m going to try and work through the backlog of DIY and to see if I can get somewhere with my side projects. I also have a chance to reflect, learn and experiment.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1&gt;The approach&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I’m going to go lean and iterate, pulling in techniques I’ve tried in isolation and ones that are new to me that I’ve wanted to experiment with for some time. I’m going to come up with a formula, try it for two weeks and then have a period to reflect on it, just like in the retrospective of a two week sprint. (More about retrospectives here) If I have changed something then I have the choice to keep on doing it, adjust it or to bin it off. Generally, I’m going to take ideas from all over, mash them together and then see what happens.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4&gt;First off&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What do I actually want to achieve? What are the typical tasks that I want to tick off? I’ve broken them down into seven categories:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;i&gt;Growth&lt;/i&gt; – learning, reading and reflection&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;i&gt;Ideation&lt;/i&gt; – coming up with new ideas and trying things out&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;i&gt;Personal branding&lt;/i&gt; – raising my profile professionally in case I have to hit the job market. Documenting, blogging, tweeting, working LinkedIn, etc.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;i&gt;Housekeeping&lt;/i&gt; – general day to day stuff. Reading and sorting through emails, blah, blha, blah…&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;i&gt;Health&lt;/i&gt; - getting the exercise that I’m sure we’ve all been missing put on recently. If I was ever going to try Yoga it would be stuck in here.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;i&gt;Preparation&lt;/i&gt; - planning what I’m going to work on today, next week and so on.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;i&gt;Slack&lt;/i&gt; – not the time sucking interruption engine that shouts at me on the app bar but more like the concept from Tom DeMarko’s book of the same name. I might go with calling it ‘Free periods’ as Slack is now such a loaded word, but I’m not going to agonise over it, I’m going to go with whatever to keep things moving.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;Secondly&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I’m going to pinch and bastardise concepts from &lt;b&gt;Getting Things Done&lt;/b&gt; by &lt;b&gt;David Allen&lt;/b&gt; and to categorise my tasks into lists. Historically I have always been able to hold a mental map of what the priorities are and to juggle tasks effectively in my head; taking notes when I need to in the trusty notebook. Working from home for about a year with constant Zoom calls, Slack doing its thing, along with the added complication of two young children who are climbing up the walls that need help with their education has put paid to that. The context switching, interruptions and not being able to take time to have general chit-chat with collegues had already forced me to change how I work, but now is the time to try and form habits.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ve created three lists:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;i&gt;Today&lt;/i&gt; – what I’m going to work on today. I fill this list in at the start of each day.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;i&gt;Tomorrow&lt;/i&gt; – a general term; it might not be tomorrow, but it’s the stuff that is coming up next.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;i&gt;Backlog&lt;/i&gt; – Everything else. Stuff that needs doing, but this may be where unimportant stuff goes to die…&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;Thirdly&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I’ve populated each list with tasks which are a bit like Story Cards on a SCRUM board after &lt;b&gt;Agile Software Development with Scrum&lt;/b&gt; by &lt;b&gt;Ken Schwaber&lt;/b&gt;. Each task has a brief description / title and a checklist of things that I need to complete to finish the task. I’d played around with the idea of using swimlanes and subtasks, but in the end decided against it as I think keeping the subtasks together with the overall task will allow me more flexibility to context switch, reprioritise and generally shuffle things around; I don’t want to be wasting time moving swimlanes and their items around when things change.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Each list has been split into four columns:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;ToDo&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;In Progress&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Blocked&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Done&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;and I’ve ordered the items in each column into a general sense of descending priority top to bottom. I don’t spend too much time on this and even though there are fewer items in ‘Today’ and ‘Backlog’ I’ve spent the same amount of time on the three lists as I don’t want to waste time prioritising tasks that I may never do. The whole prioritisation took maybe five minutes. If it takes longer then I’ve probably taken too long.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Items in each list have these properties:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Date created&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Status - ToDo, In Progress, Blocked or Done&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Discuss with – if a task needs input from someone else then I add them into this list. If I’m having a conversation with someone then I can group items together to tick off as many things as I need to.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Waiting on – similar to ‘Discuss with’ but if a task or part of it is blocked because I need someone to do something then I make a note of who I’m waiting on and what I need them to do.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Due by – so that I can make sure that I don’t miss a deadline.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Category – Growth, Ideation, Personal branding, Housekeeping, Health, Preparation, Slack.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;along with the checklist of subtasks that need to be completed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4&gt;Lastly&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I have decided to try and mix things up so that I don’t get bogged down on just one thing that’s not going anywhere. I going to try to use the  &lt;b&gt;Pomodoro Technique&lt;/b&gt; developed by &lt;b&gt;Francesco Cirillo&lt;/b&gt; back in the 80s as in a previous role I have had great success with Promiscuous Pairing from a white paper by Arlo Belshee and I can see many similarities. In short I’m going to work in dedicated 25 minute blocks, preferably without interruption. During the five minutes following a session I’m going to take a break, deal with any interruptions that came up if they can be immediately addressed. If they can’t be dealt with there and then I’ll create a new task for them and then confirm what my next 25 minute session will be focussed on. Context switching can destroy progress so I can decide if the next session is on the same subject or whether it is time to park the task and proceed onto the next priority. I’m going to be flexible and to take advantage of the fact that right now my time is broadly speaking my own. Having a check after every twenty five minutes if I want to continue on a task should hopefully be a good way of preventing me from going too far down the rabbit hole and spending too much time on a lost cause.&lt;br /&gt;
After a year of working from home I’m probably most excited about the prospect of forcing myself to take regular breaks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1&gt;Structuring my work&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I love structure and routine and lockdown has driven a bus through my working practices so this is a good chance to start from scratch. I’m going to kick off my day with all the stuff that I need to get done from a general life perspective, from getting the children ready for school to walking the dog. I’ll get that out of the way by 9am. I even have a little timetable that I knocked up. I’m not sure how much success I’ll have with that, but hey, it beats the daily commute.&lt;br /&gt;
At the start of each day, I’m going to reprioritise my lists so I know what I’m working on and as the last task on Friday I’m going to plan my upcoming week. Broadly speaking this is my opportunity to take a longer look into the backlog and to pull tasks out.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Each day I’ll try to ensure there is a mix of the seven categories that I’ve listed above with an overall focus.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1&gt;Let’s do it!&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here I go. I’ll update this post with things I’ve learned or changes I’ve made if I alter what I’m doing. The basic goal is to do more of the good stuff and less of the bad stuff and if I learn something along the way then so much the better.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="time" /><category term="management" /><category term="task" /><summary type="html">The Pandemic and lockdowns have obviously had a huge impact on how we work and have especially imposed new challenges juggling the work / life balance. In turn this has meant that some tried and tested methods for managing tasks and actually completing them are failing. This is my attempt to find another way that works for me.</summary></entry></feed>